processes are used in Unix to allocate resources to users and programs.
They're equivalent to address spaces in ZOS.
A process is created by a fork system call and it's terminated by executing an
exit system call, more by a kill signal from another process. Each process has a
unique identifier called a process ID or a PID. The fork system call creates a new
process with identical characteristics as the process that issued the fork.
The new process is called the child process and that process that created it
is called the parent process. After the fork system call, the two processes are
running exactly the same program. However, the return code from the fork
system call is different from the parent and from the child. The two processes
will also have inherited different process IDs. The child inherits the file
descriptors of the parent process which means it has access to the same files
including pipes as its parent. The exec system call is used to start a new
program in a process. The sequence of fork followed by exec system calls is
used very often in Unix to create a new process and start a new program.
Unix pipes are a way of communicating between processes. Conceptually pipes are
like a sequential file. One process can write to the pipe while another
process reads from the pipe. There are two different types of pipes as unnamed
and FIFO unnamed pipes. Unnamed pipes also refer to some signs just as pipes
are defined by a pseudo device type and the pipes are buffered in memory by
the pipe device driver. Unnamed pipes have the restriction that they can
only be used by the processes which have the same parent process. The pipe
system call is used to invoke an unnamed pipe. Processes use read and write system
calls to access the data in a pipe. FIFO or named pipes have names and reside
in the Unix file system but because of this they can be used for communication
between any two processes. A FIFO pipe must be opened by the open system
call. Only one process can access a FIFO pipe for reading or writing at a
time. Unix provides another communication method between processes
called signaling. Signals are used for communication between processes to inform
about events and trigger actions. Most signals are generated by the kernel. The
kill system call is used to send a signal to another process. The process
sending a signal must know the process ID of the receiving process. The kill
system call is so named because it's mostly used to terminate a process. The
signal system call is used for setting a trap to catch signals. The process ID
specified in the call determines who it applies to and only processes which
satisfy the criteria are the ones that accept the signal. So that covers some
of the main Unix functions which are useful to know in order to understand
ZOS Unix. But what about security? Well security in a Unix system is
based on file access security, data encryption and user logon security. Unix
files and directories are protected by permission bits. Access is granted on
three levels. There's owner, group and world or other. World is all users in
the system. Owner and group are defined when a file is created and can be
changed by commands later on. Users with common access permissions can be
gathered in a group. File permission is defined for read, write and execute access.
The system checks a user's ID for permission to access a file or
directory. Access control lists or ACLs extend the security provided by
permission bits by allowing you to control access to files and directories
by individual user ID or UID and by group or GID. Unix has two categories of
users. There's user and super user. Users must use a password to log into a Unix
system. The super user bypasses all security checking and has access to all
files. Only the super user can perform authorized functions or commands such as
mounting a file system. From here on in we'll move into some more ZOS
specifics starting in the next video with the hierarchical file system
implementation in ZOS Unix.